how many are abroad and how many
were repatriated during the pandemic
lost their jobs um were remittances
still
you know increasing during this period
what are the trends that you're seeing
here
uh yes dania thank you for that now so
you know our uh
ofw's from april to uh to september 2019
alone
the remittances have reached up to
around 211
billion pesos just uh just uh from 1.9
million filipinos who are abroad but
based on statistics around 10 of our
total population now
are currently working abroad but uh
currently as we know
um a lot of our ofw's are faced no of a
lot of challenges because of the
pandemic all over the world
sir how have the uh behavior of
remittances
uh been doing during the pandemic um
are they still some uh you know
economists have said they're sticky you
know that
in fact people send more panga um in
during times of economic crisis
is that what you are seeing that the ofw
remittances or their behaviors didn't
really change
even with the global economic situation
it has somehow didn't change but uh yeah
we see that uh with the
uh um ongoing uh uh vaccination all over
the world we see that the trend is still
going up
and in fact the contribution of our ofw
made to be one of our significant
uh um contributors to our country's
progress it remains to be the remittance
as it means to be one of our
uh sources of way of sustaining our
gdp the country sir have the
you know usage of funds changed uh
significantly so from before you know
we've had
uh you know immigration for such a long
time already
um in fact the the level of work of ofw
is now abroad is quite high level
i mean it's it's moved from domestic
work into quite high school
technical work already why is it that uh
people are not yet able to save
um and why is it that even with
increased uh you know
wealth of ofws better skill sets
um more opportunities and even the
second generation
it's still that's still the case saving
is a
discipline no it's a something that we
commit for a certain goal
so i think uh you know ofw's must be
able to have that as you mentioned a
while ago the 32 percent uh
rate of families actually saving from
the remittances
earned or received from their ofw is
really low but you know it's
it's a matter of really joint uh um
effort between families and ofws to have
this really discipline of saving
saving not only saving but investing and
really managing their wealth and
finances
to make sure that whatever goals they
have in life that will be achieved in
the near future
so i think it's really more of the why
and the how the how is something that
they're doing at the moment they're
working abroad
their sacrifices but the y should really
be very strong every day
because they should not be contented on
you know very simple saving which is uh
uh you know it's a very conservative way
but there's a lot of investment vehicles
out there
that will allow them to have better
yields of their money but at the same
time getting protected also
and getting more secured in terms of the
income that they get
as well as uh being secured or protected
in terms of their health
what can they do in the short to medium
term uh to ensure
that their finances are going to be
stable and will take them through
these difficult times yeah wealth
management and financial planning
i would advise that you know they seek
the help of a
professional life insurance professional
or a financial advisor for them to be
able to get well
guided no uh when it comes to really
achieving their financial objectives so
i think that's one
but really having this comprehensive
financial block is
important doesn't matter how much we
earn what's important is how much we
save and what we do with the savings
that we have
i think as an ofw it should be a
partnership between the ofw
who works abroad at the same time the
family is
who's here not uh they're the ones who's
receiving the
remittances and they're the reason why
the ofw the ofw is abroad